(dramatic music)
- [Narrator] France!
July 26th, 1794!
Anarchy,
misery,
murder,
arson,
fear!
These are the weapons of dictatorship!
One voice is heard!
The screech of the guillotine!
France lies bleeding, Paris an open wound.
The grab for power is on!
Maximilian Robespierre,
a fanatic with touted
wig and twisted mind.
Saint Just,
connoisseur of roses and blood.
Fouche the politician,
always on both sides, never in the middle.
Danton the soldier,
savior of France.
Francois Barras, citizen of the republic.
An honest man fighting for
the life of his country.
Tallien, another honest man.
In 48 hours France will have a dictator!
In 48 hours!
Unless...
(wild music)
- [Marquis] It's a sad day when
Frenchmen have to meet on enemy soil.
- The Reign of Terror swept
to the borders of France.
All the liberties we fought
for in the revolution
are being destroyed.
- Who is in power now?
- Maximilian Robespierre.
He's demanding dictatorship.
- He's a madman.
France must never have a dictator.
- You're the only man who
could stop him, General.
- I'm in exile, Charles,
a political prisoner.
I don't dare escape from Austria.
My face is too well-known.
You'll have to take my place.
- Your orders, sir.
- I no longer give orders.
I'm no longer the Marquis de Lafayette.
A general without an army.
A Frenchman without a country.
All I can do is give you my blessing.
There's a man in Strasbourg
who will help you.
Show him this ring.
(galloping music)
(moves into ominous music)
- Who are you?
From the Marquis de Lafayette.
You have come just in time.
The plans are all set.
(dramatic music)
- Death!
I demand death for the enemies of France.
I denounce Danton!
I demand death for Danton!
- I demand the right to be heard!
- Traitor!
- [Danton] Assassin!
- You stand accused, guilty, condemned.
- Who accuses me?
- I, Robespierre.
- Dictator!
- Silence!
Your trial is over!
- It hasn't begun!
- Citizens!
What is your will?
(crowd murmuring)
Death!
(crowd screaming)
- Citizens!
Open your eyes!
Tomorrow it may be you standing here,
accused, condemned, unheard!
(crowd shouting)
Beware, Robespierre!
The blood of Danton will
choke in your throat!
(crowd shouting)
- If you've come to beg
for your husband's life,
you are late.
- Maximilian, what has come over you?
Danton is your friend,
your very good friend.
Together you saved France!
Without Danton, where would you be today?
- I can't let personal feelings interfere.
The people have found him guilty.
- The people?
But you're the people!
They do what you say!
- Take out an appeal.
- Who can I appeal to?
Only you?
Look at me!
Answer me!
Stop playing God!
- God?
The revolution abolished God.
It's only the will of the people,
and the people have spoken.
(Madame Danton sobs)
(banging on the door)
That's my chair you're sitting in, Fouche.
- I just wanted to see how it fits.
- [Maximilian] Danton liked
to sit in that chair too.
- And to think that he had
supper with us only last night.
Ah, it's amazing how fast
you lose friends these days.
- And you never know who's
next on the list, Fouche.
- It must be quite a thrill
making out your death list every night.
Well, you sent for me, here I am.
What's on your mind?
- I can't decide whether to
promote you or denounce you.
- Where in all Paris
would you find anybody as
disloyal, unscrupulous,
scheming, treacherous, cunning,
or deceitful as I?
Oh, (laughs) you'd have to
do some tall looking, Max.
- Don't call me Max!
- You're not dictator, yet.
- I will be.
- Not without my help.
I know too much about you.
- Get out of my chair.
- Is that the way to talk to
your chief of secret police?
I'm ashamed of you, Max.
- Citizen Barras.
- I arrived just in time
to see Danton on his way out,
exactly as you planned, wasn't it?
- [Maximilian] Danton
was my friend, not yours.
Why should you feel badly about it?
- Because Danton was a good soldier.
Without him, France would've been overrun
by the armies of Europe.
- That was yesterday.
Like all good soldiers, he
outlived his usefulness.
Read that.
- What is it?
- It's a motion I want you to
place before the convention.
- Why, this would make
you dictator of France.
- Yes.
- [Francois] We didn't storm the Bastille
to make any man dictator!
- I am not any man.
- I and my party will support no man
until there is an end
to this mob violence,
secret police and the wholesale murder.
- What you call mob violence
is the Committee of Public Safety,
which enjoys the confidence of the people.
Anyone who challenges the committee
is an enemy of the people.
Where do you belong, citizen Barras?
- Not in this room.
- I don't think you
handled that too well, Max.
- Barras is not a man to
be intimidated by words.
- He's the only man who can
recommend you for dictator
before the convention.
You can't chop his head off.
- No, but Barras has many devoted friends.
When their heads begin to fall,
I'll think he'll come around
to my way of thinking.
- There's no one in Paris who'd
dare touch any of his party.
Not even I.
- No, but there's a man in Strasbourg
who isn't afraid of anything.
A man named Duval.
- Du what?
- Do you know him?
- No, but I know his record.
500 executions in a single month.
That's almost as good as yours, Max.
- I've sent for Duval.
He arrives at the Blue Goose Inn tonight.
You go there and bring him to the bakery.
I'll meet him there.
- How will I know him?
- As one snake to another,
you'll smell each other out.
(knocking on the door)
- Welcome, citizen, welcome.
- I'm Duval, public
prosecutor of Strasbourg.
- Will you have dinner?
- Just show me to my room.
(suspicious music)
I'm expecting an escort from Paris.
See that I'm not disturbed until he comes.
- Rest assured, citizen Duval.
Good night, citizen.
(ominous music)
(Duval screams)
(crazy music)
(knocking on the door)
(mysterious music)
- [Innkeeper] I'm sorry, but
there is no room to be had.
- I've come to see citizen Duval.
- He left orders not to be disturbed.
- He'll see me!
Which is his room?
- Please do not make a disturbance!
Come back tomorrow!
- Which door?
Or must I awaken all of your guests?
- All right, first door to the left.
(knocking on the door)
- Who's there?
- [Madelon] A messenger from Paris.
- Don't move.
What's the message?
- It's so dark in here.
- I can hear in the dark.
Speak.
- It's a written message.
I need light.
- There's a candle on the bureau.
- Light it for me.
- Just
hand me the message and you can go.
- I was told to wait for an answer.
Please light the candle.
- Why are you so anxious
for a lightened room?
Don't you recognize the voice of Duval?
- I've never met you
before, citizen Duval.
- Well if you don't know me,
what good will a light do?
Or are you afraid I might not be Duval?
- Who else could you be?
- That depends on who sent the message.
- Only two men in Paris can
send messages beyond the border.
Robespierre and Barras.
- Which one sent you?
- That's a dangerous question
to answer in the dark.
- One of us has to make the first move.
- Courtesy demands you speak first.
- Barras.
- Thank heaven.
What happened to the real Duval?
- He's dead.
- What did you do with the body?
- My men were waiting below.
Quick, what's the message?
Robespierre's men will come
to pick me up at any minute.
- Barras wants you to
report to Robespierre,
gain his confidence,
even if you must betray some
of us to keep his confidence.
A few lives won't matter,
but Robespierre must
never become dictator.
- How can I prevent that?
- You'll get further orders from Paris.
- From whom?
- From me.
- Well, if we're to recognize each other,
I suppose we might as well have a look.
- Charles!
- You're looking very well, Madelon.
I had no idea such prosperity
went with the revolution.
- You don't seem to have
suffered much either.
- What did you expect me
to do when you walked out,
stop breathing?
- I couldn't explain to you the--
- You can explain now.
We'll have a bottle of
wine over old times.
Perhaps I can get the innkeeper to come up
and play the violin.
Explanations always
sound better with music.
- I don't blame you for hating me.
- I don't like to deprive you
of that satisfaction, Madelon.
I don't hate you.
I just don't care anymore.
- I'll be at the Cafe Velavinted.
After seeing Robespierre,
please come there Charles.
Please.
- Seems I remember an appointment
we had four years ago.
Only one of us showed up.
The stupid one.
Well Charles has grown
up to be a smart boy now.
- I'll be waiting.
- I wouldn't count the minutes.
(afflicted music)
- Who's that?
- She came to see citizen Duval.
- Hm.
Interesting.
(mysterious music)
- [Innkeeper] Citizen
Duval, your escort has...
- What's the matter with you?
- You look so different, citizen Duval.
(suspenseful music)
- Different?
Why should the appearance
of a public prosecutor
interest you so much, citizen?
You haven't by chance a guilty conscience?
- No no, citizen prosecutor.
I'm a patriot!
It was the wig, yes of course, the wig!
(foreboding music)
- So.
You're the terror of Strasbourg.
- (laughs) I'd recognize you
anywhere, citizen Fouche.
- You had a visitor, I see.
- All work and no play?
- I thought you enjoyed your work.
- The uh, real pleasure of my work
went outwith the guillotine.
It's all over too fast now.
Even hanging.
That lasts but a few moments.
No, citizen Fouche.
What this country needs
is an elegant, slow death.
Give a man four hours to die.
It's worth watching.
- Let's try it sometime, shall we?
Anyone in particular?
Robespierre has a beautiful long list.
We're gonna have some great
times together, eh Duval?
- Yes, I can hardly wait.
(Charles and Fouche laughing)
- Duval,
you don't know me and I don't know you.
- That's a good start.
- We, uh, might be able to
do each other some good.
What do you think?
- You haven't said anything yet.
- Suppose you tell me why
Robespierre sent for you.
- I was just going to ask you that.
- (laughs) Come, Duval.
You can trust me.
- Can I?
- No
(Fouche and Duval laughing)
(frenzied music)
(gunshot fires)
(Fouche coughs)
One thing about Paris, never dull.
- Dull?
(troubled music)
What is this?
- Robespierre's headquarters.
- A bakery?
- He loves hot biscuits
in the morning. (laughs)
(shadowy music)
- Welcome to Paris, citizen Duval.
- It's a pleasure.
- I never shake hands.
It's unsanitary.
- Your barber?
- Mm.
Ask him again where it is.
- Where is it?
(barber moans)
(barber screams)
- Why don't you eat your bun?
Good, mm?
- Delicious.
- Remove the body.
The people of Paris are becoming
more stubborn every day.
- We have the same trouble in Strasbourg.
- I congratulate you on your record there.
- It was becoming monotonous.
- We'll do our very best to
make it exciting for you here.
- Fouche, why don't you take a walk?
- The streets aren't safe
this hour of the night.
Oh Well.
- I expected an older man.
- So did I.
- I'm the eldest of our group.
This past May I was 36.
Fouche's 35 and
Danton would've been 34 had he lived.
How old are you?
- I, uh, hope to reach your age anyway.
However, age makes men tolerant
and, uh, these are no times for tolerance.
- We're living in a
perpetual state of violence.
The people have become
a blood-thirsting mob
that thrives on human lives.
Each day this monster
must drink its quota.
There's only one man who
can control this beast
and that man must be dictator of France.
- What's there to stop you?
- [Maximilian] A black book.
- A black book?
- My secret file.
In it a list of the names
of all the enemies of France
and the proof of their crimes.
It's in this book that I select
the daily quota for the guillotine.
Yesterday this book disappeared.
- Well uh, why not make up another one?
- You don't understand.
Some of the names are men
who work on my own committee.
They suspect, yet nobody knows for sure,
whether his name's on the list.
It's this fear which gives
me control of the convention.
Once they know they're on the
list, they'll all join forces.
I can hold them one by
one, but not as a group.
That's why it's imperative
that I get this black book back
before its contents become known.
That's the real reason why I sent for you.
Nobody knows about it but you.
- Whom do you suspect of taking it?
- I know of only one man
who, if he had the book,
would have the courage
to use it against me.
Barras, one of the leaders
of the opposition party.
- I'd, uh, like to meet this Barras.
- Well it won't be easy.
He's gone into hiding
until the convention meets.
You'll act a special agent
for the Committee of Public Safety.
Here's your authority for power
over all police personnel.
- Fouche too?
- Over everyone.
Except me.
You have 24 hours.
- Not much time.
- [Maximilian] Convention
meets day after tomorrow.
We must have the book back by then.
- And if I fail?
- As you said, Duval,
these are no times for tolerance.
I don't tolerate failures.
- Well.
Where we do we start?
- Start what?
- Whatever it is.
Aren't we going to work together?
- I think tonight calls for a one-man job.
- [Fouche] Well I'm the man.
- Yes, but she might not like the idea.
- [Fouche] Can't your diversions wait?
- (laughs) You see, I may
only be in Paris 24 hours.
All right, driver.
(singing in a foreign language)
- Wait around the corner.
- All by yourself, citizen?
- Madelon is expecting me.
- Sit down.
Sit down.
(singing in a foreign language)
- Nice evening, gentlemen.
- You wish to see Madelon?
- She told me to meet her here.
- Who are you?
- A friend of Madelon.
- So was I once.
- Here she comes.
(singing in a foreign language)
- You wanted to see me?
- I asked to see Madelon.
- I am Madelon.
- At uh, another time,
in another place,
I might accept you as Madelon.
- That will be all, Evelyn.
- He's nice.
- I haven't got all night, citizen.
- Don't just sit.
Order something.
(singing in a foreign language)
(people applauding)
- If it isn't the terror of Strasbourg.
- I don't think we were introduced.
- Saint Just is the name.
The shadow of Robespierre.
Wherever he goes, I go.
Except here.
He doesn't like women.
Come on, join my party.
- Some other time, Saint Just.
- You don't like women either?
- I'm a little tired tonight.
- No one goes to bed in Paris.
It isn't safe to go to bed.
I've had so many friends,
all killed in bed.
Fouche's secret police.
- Thanks for warning me.
- [Saint Just] I have
a friend in Strasbourg,
Henry Duponte.
No doubt you know him.
- I uh, can't say that I do.
- Good.
He doesn't live in Strasbourg.
- (laughs) That's very amusing.
- You know something?
I don't think you are Duval.
- No?
- You don't look like a butcher.
- On first glance one could almost
mistake you for a human being.
- [Woman] Saint Just!
We missed you!
- You see, I am a human being.
(singing in a foreign language)
- This way.
(lively music)
(Charles grunts)
You choose your friends unwisely.
Saint Just is an enemy.
Who sent you?
- [Man] Shall we finish him?
- Not here.
(singing in a foreign language)
- Thanks for a most cordial reception.
- My friends are sometimes too impersonal.
Come on up, Charles.
(singing in a foreign language)
- Close the door, Charles.
Come over here, Charles.
Closer.
(enchanting music)
- Just one kiss and four
years are wiped out.
Life's not that simple, Madelon.
Not even for you.
- Go on.
Pour out your bitterness.
- I drank it up
in buckets of sweet wine.
- Tell me about the women
that went with the wine.
- They were all called Madelon.
They had your eyes, your
mouth.
And the same false smile.
- Tell me more.
Make me jealous.
- They even kissed like you,
with soft, warm lips.
- Like this?
(passionate music)
- Exactly.
- You are a stranger, Charles.
We really don't know each other anymore.
- But I have no intention of
renewing the acquaintance.
- [Madelon] Then why did
you come here tonight?
- To find Barras.
Unfortunately, you're my only contact.
- Why should you want to help him?
- Because I'm a Frenchman.
And there's only one
man who can save France
and put an end to this terror.
Barras.
- I wish I were that confident.
I trust this man, Madelon.
Even though he doesn't
have the usual reaction
to your charm.
Have you met with Robespierre?
- [Charles] I just left him.
- Were you followed?
- I'm sure I was, but
there was no time to lose.
Day after tomorrow he's
going to ask the convention
to appoint him dictator.
- Robespierre must never become dictator.
- Ever hear of the black book?
- The death list.
- [Charles] Well the book's gone.
- Who has it?
- [Charles] Well I was hoping it was you.
- If only I did have it.
I could put the entire convention
into a frenzy against him.
- It's the secret police!
They've got the cafe surrounded!
- You'll have to go this way!
Hurry!
Quick!
(frenzied music)
- Just one more kiss and
I'd have melted. (laughs)
(stormy music)
- Citizen Barras, you're under arrest.
- He's my prisoner.
- Was.
- Is.
- I'm afraid you're a
little confused, Duval.
I'm the chief of police.
- You were chief of police.
My authorization from Robespierre.
Now if you'll be so kind as to leave.
(sneaky music)
- Good work, Duval.
I was afraid Fouche was
going to outsmart you.
Come in, Barras.
(somber music)
You've had a strenuous day, Duval.
I'll see that our friend
gets to prison safely.
Good night.
(unpleasant music)
(Charles shouts)
- Upstairs.
(troubled music)
- Madelon--
- Shut up!
Your friend delivered Barras
right into the hands of Saint Just.
- That wasn't part of my plan.
- I saw it with my own eyes.
- What are you waiting for, Tellian?
Shoot him.
- Which side are you on?
- Well, it looks like I'm in the middle.
But if you give me a chance
I might be able to save Barras.
- We're wasting time.
- For heaven's sakes, Madelon,
can't you see I'm not lying?
- [Madelon] Frankly, no.
- Just because I refused a
kiss, you'd have me killed.
Since when have you put
such a price on your kisses?
- Shoot him!
- You know I'm not Duval, so does she!
Give me a chance to free Barras.
- There are only three men in our party
who could possibly have the book.
You know who they are.
- [Tellian] If he's lying
we can get rid of him later.
It's worth the risk.
(suspenseful music)
(knocking on the door)
- Lambert.
- Exciting enough for you, citizen Duval?
You've seen Castel and
Bernard and now Lambert.
Somebody got here first.
- Then you know about--
- The black book, mm-hm.
Nobody keeps secrets from me.
- Nothing has been disturbed
in any of the rooms.
- Your, uh, companion has good eyes.
No one of these men
ever had the black book.
- Then why were they silenced?
- Only Robespierre can answer that.
- Or perhaps you, citizen Fouche.
"Who?
Me'?
(gloomy music)
- Well, much as I dislike
to tear myself away,
looks as though I'll have to,
unless of course you still
insist on shooting me.
- I made a mistake, Charles.
- Your mistake almost cost me my life.
- Your life isn't worth
much unless you save Barras.
- That doesn't sound like the Madelon
who had her arms around me a while ago,
but I guess you're pretty free
with your arms these days,
aren't you?
- Don't tempt me.
I still have the gun.
- What ever happened to
the Madelon I once knew?
- You had a chance to find out.
That chance won't come again.
- You're sure of that?
- Positive.
(romantic music)
- Still wanna shoot me?
- I could kill you.
(passionate music)
- There's a revolution going on.
Don't stay out late.
- What you say, Saint Just, disturbs me.
- I'm not sure, but it looked as if
he were trying to help Barras to escape.
- [Anthony] The man's record is perfect.
- Duval's record is perfect.
- Huh?
What do you mean?
- Fouche told me about an
incident that happened at the inn.
The innkeeper didn't
seem to recognize Duval
the second time he saw him.
- I need proof.
Duval's a powerful man in Strasbourg.
I can't afford to antagonize
his element there.
- You'll have proof.
His wife arrives at noon today.
- Citizen Duval.
- Send him in.
- Well, good morning, gentlemen.
We had a profitable night.
Barras is in prison and
three of his best men dead.
- What about the book?
- That's why I'm here.
- Your time is getting short.
- Why did you kill Castel,
Bernard, and Lambert last night?
- What makes you think it was me?
- It wasn't Fouche,
Barras is in prison,
and I didn't do it.
That leads only you, Saint Just.
- Let credit fall where credit is due.
- I'll never find the book
if he keeps killing off the
only people I can question.
- Dead enemies make good friends.
- You know, if I'm to be
of any service to you,
you've got to take me
into your confidence.
- [Maximilian] What is
it you'd like to know?
- In all three rooms of the slain men,
nothing was disturbed.
No attempt was made to
search for the black book.
I want to know why.
- Perhaps you'd better
answer that, Saint Just.
- You have the reputation for
being a clever man, Duval.
Suppose you find the answers.
- Thank you.
I will.
(suspicious music)
- We should hold him till we're sure!
- I always believe in
giving a man enough rope.
(woman sobbing)
- I've come to question
the prisoner Barras.
- The Committee of
Public Safety's authority
is good enough for me.
Just shout when you're finished.
- Barras.
- What do you want?
(glass shattering)
- I didn't turn you in, Barras.
- Saint Just just happened
to be in your carriage?
- You've got to trust me.
I'm here to help you.
- I don't need your help,
citizen prosecutor, terror of Strasbourg!
- I'm not Duval.
I'm Charles D'Aubigny.
- Lafayette.
- I'm his agent.
- What trick is it this time?
- Last night Castel, Bernard,
and Lambert were assassinated.
- By whom?
- Saint Just.
- Then it's all over.
- There's only one way I can save you.
We've got to find that black book.
- I told you it was none of my men.
- Then why were they killed last night?
- Part of some fiendish
plot of Robespierre.
- None of the rooms of the
murdered men were searched.
If they weren't killed for the black book,
what's behind it all?
- Fear.
Divide and conquer.
Plot as old as Caesar.
Robespierre's plan is
to break up the party.
Since the book disappeared
some of my men have already
come to distrust each other.
Last night's murders will
make them even more unsure.
By the time the convention meets,
there'll be no one to
oppose his dictatorship.
- But if the book's still missing,
how will we dare face the convention?
Some of his own men are
listed in that book.
- Then why haven't they come forward?
Whoever has it wouldn't keep silent.
- One man would.
- Who?
- Robespierre.
- Robespierre?
- He never lost the book.
It was never out of his possession.
- Then why--
- Don't you see what he
accomplished with a single lie?
He's had us all on a wild goose chase
searching for something
that was never lost.
That's why those rooms weren't disturbed.
There was nothing to look for.
- If he has it,
then he will become dictator.
- [Charles] Guard!
Guard!
- D'Aubigny.
If you should find it and I'm not there,
give it to Tallien.
He'll have the courage to use it.
- You'll be there.
Hurry up, guard!
Guard!
- What's your hurry, my friend?
The convention doesn't meet till tomorrow.
- [Charles] Unlock this door.
- Is that an order?
- [Charles] It's a command.
- By whose authority?
- [Charles] By authority of Robespierre.
- Just a precaution, Duval.
If you are Duval.
By the way, I have good news for you.
Your wife is on her way from Strasbourg.
She should be here at any minute now.
Why don't you just relax until she comes?
Robespierre and I wouldn't
wanna miss the happy reunion.
- [Man] Citizen Robespierre!
(everyone shouting)
- What are your prisoners doing out here?
- This is today's batch
for the guillotine.
- Shoot them out!
(people screaming)
(gunshots firing)
- Citizeness Duval, Saint Just.
- [Saint Just] Greetings.
Fetch citizen Duval.
- I apologize for inconveniencing you.
- I was looking for an
excuse to get to Paris.
There are so many things I want to buy.
(dramatic music)
(Madelon laughs)
(perplexed music)
- Bobo!
Bobo, Bobo, Bobo!
Bobo, what are you doing in jail?
- Well I--
- [Mme. Duval] Now what
has the silly boy done?
- Nothing.
It was just a slight misunderstanding.
My apologies, Duval.
You see, in my position,
one can't be too careful.
- I compliment you on your thoroughness.
You too, Saint Just.
- Come, Bobo.
We have so much to do.
- (laughs) Yes, my love.
- Wait for me.
I was told I could find
citizen Robespierre here.
- And who wishes to see
citizen Robespierre?
- Madame Duval.
- Inform citizen Robespierre that
Madame Duval desires an audience.
- I'm not accustomed
to being kept waiting.
- Perhaps citizen Saint Just can help you.
- At your service, Madame.
- I'll speak to no one
but citizen Robespierre.
- We all make mistakes.
- No one's perfect.
- [Anthony] Where's Madame Duval?
- I am Madame Duval.
- [Anthony] Get him!
(galloping music)
- That was close.
How'd you know about Duval's wife?
- Uh, one of our men
recognized her at the border.
Lucille took her place.
(escaping music)
(horse neighs)
(gunshot fires)
We've got to get out of Paris.
- Drop me at the bakery.
(troubled music)
- Greetings, Duval.
- Greetings, patriot.
Has Robespierre returned?
- He's over at the prison
on some important business.
- (laughs) That's what I like to hear.
(ominous music)
- [Guard] Greetings, citizen Duval.
- Greetings, patriot.
(dog barking)
Greetings, patriot.
(uneasy music)
Nice patriot.
(veiled music)
(heavy thudding)
- Greetings to you, patriot.
Last I heard you were in jail.
- That fool Saint Just
didn't think I was Duval.
- But of course you proved otherwise.
- Of course.
- Saint Just is a fool.
Ah ah ah ah, please Charles.
No violence.
- You once spoke about
working together, Fouche.
- The offer I made was to Duval.
But I'd make to you the same offer.
After all, we're both
out for the same thing.
- But I know where it is.
- Where?
- What are you after?
- Once Robespierre is eliminated,
I want joint power with Barras.
- Only Barras can give you that.
- Barras is in no position to bargain now.
What's your answer, me or Robespierre?
- You're the lesser of two evils, Fouche.
You have my word.
We break into this room.
- What for?
- The black book.
- In Robespierre's own room?
- It was never out of that room.
- What?
Oh. (laughs)
What a clever rascal.
I'm afraid I underestimated Max.
- [Charles] Hurry up, Fouche.
- You forget this is not
my regular profession.
(metal rattling)
(shadowy music)
It's not in the desk.
- [Charles] It's got to be in this room.
(mysterious music)
- VVell.
There's your black book.
All you have to do is
to find the right one.
- It'll take forever
to go through all this.
- Maybe we'll be lucky.
You start over there.
(questing music)
(door creaking)
(suspenseful music)
(moves into calm music)
(moves into puzzled music)
- Fouche!
Fouche!
Look at the names!
- Is my name in it?
- Let's see.
Barras.
Lafayette.
Tallien.
Berdam.
Fouche.
(menacing music)
(Fouche chokes)
(ominous music)
(crowd shouting)
- Seize him!
(dramatic music)
(gunshot fires)
(glass shattering)
Do something!
(stormy music)
(body thuds)
(glass shattering)
(gunshot fires)
- Some cabbages, citizen?
Freshly cut last night.
- Artichokes?
- Pierre.
This customer is asking for artichokes.
- Artichokes are out of season.
- I was told I could find some here.
- They're very expensive.
How many did you want?
- Three large, three small.
- [Madelon] I thought
you'd never get here.
- I almost didn't.
- [Tallien] Did you find it?
- Those gendarmes are going
through the marketplace.
They must be looking for you.
- [Tallien] Won't be
safe anywhere in Paris!
- What about your sister's farm?
- [Tallien] Good.
You can hide out there until
the convention meets tomorrow.
Keep this.
It will be safer with you.
(crowd screaming)
- I'll go with Charles.
- Never get out of the
city in those clothes.
I'll get you some others.
- We'll meet tomorrow at daybreak
in the Cafe of the Living Dead.
Good luck.
(crowd screaming)
(horses neighing)
- Where are your papers?
- I told you, I lost them.
But ask anyone in the market.
They'll tell you who we are.
- I am not interested in who you are,
but who you gave your papers too.
- [Marie] Is it against the
law to lose one's papers?
- No, but it's treason to
give them to a traitor!
- Well if a traitor found our
papers, we can't help that.
- Where is your horse and cart?
- In the stables where
we always leave them.
- Your stall is empty.
- Oh, well, they have been stolen.
- Arrest them!
Make them talk!
- [Sergeant] They won't talk now.
- [Saint Just] We'll
catch them at the farm.
Come on.
Yah!
- Show your papers.
Farmers, huh?
- No.
I'm the viscount Charles D'Aubigny
and this is Marie Antoinette. (laughs)
- See here where you passed
through only this morning
with a full load of cabbages.
Sure sold them awfully fast.
- There are a lot of
hungry people in Paris.
- [Guard] Where is your farm?
- About four kilometers from here.
- Then you must pass through here often.
Don't recall seeing your faces before.
- Cabbages don't grow
overnight, my friend.
- What else do you raise?
- Chickens, pigs.
- Pierre.
I'll uh, let you through on one condition.
- What's that?
- Next time you come through,
you bring us a couple of chickens.
- I don't know, you'll have
to ask my wife about that.
- One chicken.
- Two chickens.
- [Madelon] Small ones.
- Not too small.
(Weighty music)
(moves into galloping music)
(moves into uncertain music)
(knocking on the door)
- [Lady] Yes?
- We're friends of Pierre.
- What's happened?
- Oh nothing.
Pierre will be here tomorrow.
We'd like to stay for the night.
- Come in.
(troubled music)
Have you had your supper?
- Not yet.
- I just want a bed.
- Who are you?
- I'm the terror of Strasbourg.
(puzzled music)
(children laughing)
- Come on now, finish your milk.
And off to bed.
(expressive music)
Sit down.
- Thank you.
Are they Pierre's?
- Yes.
It's a pity they have to
grow up in times like these.
- Or you can be thankful
they don't live in Paris.
- Sometimes I wish that
Louis were still king.
- Don't say that.
We're never going back.
We're trying to build a better world.
It's not easy.
But we're never going back.
- Does anyone know where we're heading?
Did you ever live on a farm?
- I was born on one.
What is it?
- Look.
Wake your man, run to the fields!
I'll hide the cart.
- Charles!
Charles, wake up!
The soldiers are coming!
Charles!
(frantic music)
- That way.
(dramatic music)
- Anybody home?
(child cries)
ls anybody home?
- Just grandma.
- [Saint Just] Where is she?
- Bringing in Celeste.
- [Saint Just] Who is Celeste?
- My, my, my cow.
- Where's your mother and father?
- [Child] They, they went to the market.
- Have you seen any strangers?
Have you?
- What do you want here?
- We're looking for a man and woman,
traitors to the republic.
- Well, you won't find them in that bed.
(troubled music)
- This is the farm of Pierre
and Marie Blanchard, isn't it?
- Pierre is my son.
- Your son and his wife have
been arrested for treason.
- No.
- If we don't find the traitors,
they'll both be executed tomorrow.
If you know anything, grandma,
you better speak up now.
- I know nothing.
- You'll never get anything
out of these farmers.
(mysterious music)
All right, search the fields.
- [Saint Just] Bring
me some food and wine.
- Certainly.
(suspenseful music)
- I'm thirsty, grandma!
Who's that man?
- A soldier of the republic.
- [Child] What's he want?
- He's thirsty too.
- Come here, little one.
Would you like to be a
soldier when you grow up?
You could have a horse, sword,
and a gun.
You'd like that, wouldn't you?
But a good soldier never lies.
He always tells the truth.
Have you seen any strangers today,
a man and a woman?
You can tell me.
One soldier to another.
- Will I get a horse?
- You can have mine.
(Cat yowls)
Well?
- I didn't see anybody!
- More wine for a soldier of the republic?
(bitter music)
Swine.
- [Saint Just] What's that you said?
- Some more wine?
- Well?
- Not a trace of them, anywhere.
- Can't get very far
with a horse and cart.
- Maybe they've gone to the next town.
- They've got to be in
Paris by tomorrow morning.
This is as far as they'd go.
Keep searching.
- I left the men those orders.
- I'm dead on my feet.
I'm going to take a nap.
Wake me up in a half an hour.
- You're not going to
disturb the children?
- I'll take the cot.
Get me a pillow.
(ominous music)
Never mind.
(trembling music)
I said never mind!
(suspenseful music)
- [Sergeant] What are you doing?
- I was just covering him.
- Get away from there.
(defeated music)
- It's Saint Just.
- Where?
- Sleeping on the cot.
- He must've found the book.
- No, he'd be gone now if he had.
He must be sleeping right
on it if it's still there.
No no, don't get up.
There's a sergeant sitting at the table.
- The soldiers will be back any minute.
(tapping on the glass)
(children screaming)
- [Saint Just] Get in
there and put a stop to it!
(children shouting)
(frenzied music)
(horse neighs)
(gunshots firing)
- We're safe now I think.
- No, wait a minute.
We didn't lose them.
(tense music)
They'll overtake us riding double.
We'd better hide in here.
- These woods are full of caverns.
They can't search every one of them.
(troubled music)
Think they've gone?
- I better have a look.
- Spread your men outside the woods.
We'll wait here for them to come out.
- They're laying a trap
for us in the woods.
There must be another way to Paris.
- Only the main road.
- If only the moon weren't so bright,
we could make a run for it.
- We'd better wait.
Maybe the clouds will cover the moon.
There are the clouds.
You'll have to ride fast.
Don't look back.
(horse neighs)
(Madelon screams)
- Where has Charles
D'Aubigny taken the book?
To whom?
I'm asking you for the last time.
(Madelon whimpers)
Make her talk!
(Madelon cries out)
(suffering music)
(Madelon screams)
- Up to your old tricks, eh?
I know a much better way
to get the black book.
- What is your way?
It has to be quick.
The convention meets in less than an hour.
- Let her down.
This earring will have more persuasion
than any of your tortures.
I'll meet you at the convention.
- You've done well, Charles.
This day will see the end of the terror.
- I'll go back for Madelon now.
- Take some men with you.
- Please, gentlemen.
Not so rough.
Congratulations.
You came very close, Charles.
- Not quite close enough, it seems.
- Oh, I uh, have something for you.
- Where is she?
Where is she!
- Being entertained by Robespierre.
It's either Madelon or the book.
You can't have both.
- The convention meets
in less than 10 minutes.
Without this, Robespierre
will become dictator,
whereon many more will die.
France will die.
(crowd roaring)
- Bring the prisoner Francois Barras.
(crowd booing)
- This is not a trial.
Barras is not a prisoner of the bar.
You are not judges.
You are statesmen and
representatives of the nation.
In your hands lies the fate of France.
You have not to pass sentence
for or against a single man.
This man is already a
self-confessed traitor
by opposing the will of the convention.
It is you, the members of the convention,
who must take a resolution on
the question of public safety,
and to decide a question
of national foresight.
It is with regret that I
pronounce the fatal truth.
Barras ought to perish
rather than this convention
be torn with disunity.
Barras must die,
that the country may live.
(dramatic music)
- Madelon!
Madelon!
- There is a cord about
the throat of liberty,
and both ends I held my traitors
like Barras and his party!
I demand a decree of
accusation against them!
I demand a declaration
of national emergency!
I demand a suspension
of all legal procedures!
I demand that this
convention by unanimous vote
vest in me the authority of
sole and absolute dictatorship!
- Never!
- No!
- Down with dictators!
- I denounce Robespierre!
- We must uphold liberty!
- Never!
- No dictator for France!
- [Anthony] Citizens!
You'll destroy yourselves!
- I denounce Robespierre!
- Down with Robespierre!
(crowd screaming)
- Down on his head!
- Danton's blood will
choke in your throat!
- Take him to the guillotine!
(crowd screaming)
- Citizens!
(gunshot fires)
- Max, Max, they'll kill us!
- Death is no stranger to me.
- The mob's gone mad,
they'll tear us to pieces!
- I made the mob.
The mob are my children.
They won't turn against their father.
(banging on the door) (crowd screaming)
If it is my life you want, take it.
One more life isn't important.
What is important is
the will of the people.
I fought to give the people the right
to exercise their own will.
I fought to give France
back to the people.
Blood has poured freely.
If more blood is needed,
you can have mine.
The greatest death that a man
can die is for his own people.
But you will be a mob without a leader.
If I go, who takes my place?
Let the man step forward
who can follow in the
steps of Robespierre.
I have led you through the darkness.
If I sought the power of dictatorship,
it is not for personal glory.
Your will is my will.
I bear no man vengeance.
- Shut his mouth.
- [Anthony] I have killed only for you.
(gunshot fires)
(crowd screaming)
- Where is she, Saint Just, where is she!
- Only Robespierre knows!
- Take him to the guillotine!
What have you done with Madelon!
- It's no use.
He'll never speak again.
- To the guillotine!
(crowd screaming)
(singing in a foreign language)
(crashing)
(men grunting)
(men shouting)
(crowd shouting) (drum roll pounding)
(crowd cheers)
- Robespierre's last monuments.
He planned on having
statues built of himself.
All he leaves behind him is stale bread.
- [Man With Hat] The end is
always being put to some use
in France, citizen.
The art of being a Frenchman
is knowing what comes next.
- Have you any idea?
- [Man With Hat] I am neither
a Frenchman nor a politician.
I am merely a soldier.
- Well there friend, must be off.
Perhaps we shall meet again sometime.
Oh uh, by the way, I don't
believe I got your name.
- [Napoleon] My name is
Bonaparte, Napoleon Bonaparte.
- Napoleon Bonaparte.
I'll try to remember that.
(singing in a foreign language)
(fireworks booming)